# **Michael Woodruff**

# **User Experience Architect**

michaelwoodruff.com • michael.woodruff@gmail.com • (513) 410-1485

#### **SUMMARY**

A designer who focuses on creating elegant yet usable interactive experiences that engage users, while also communicating a timely effective message. Understands the need to balance the conflicting agendas of the client's business goals, user's expectations, limitations of a chosen technology, and a project's budget constraints. A firm believer that it's not only how the software looks, but also how intuitive it is to use.

### **SPECIALTIES**

E-Commerce Consulting
User Experience Design SEO/Analytics
User Interface Design Patterns A/B Testing
Whiteboard Ninja User Research
Design Systems Usability Testing
Wireframing Personas

Prototyping Adobe XD Invision/Invision Studio Sketch

Figma Framer X

Agile/Scrum

### **EXPERIENCE**

NOVEMBER 2016 — APRIL 2020

Information Architecture

### **Paycor** — Senior Product Designer

- Supporting multiple agile teams by providing user insights, user flows, wireframes, and prototypes
- Conducted and lead various methods of user research including user interviews and surveys

Journey Mapping

Collaborate with the Product Design team to create a standard user experience across all products

NOVEMBER 2016 - PRESENT

# **Western & Southern Financial Group** — User Experience Architect

- Lead User Experience Architect on corporate-wide redesign project
- Prototype new designs with modern interactive tools
- Pioneered design systems and reusable design patterns across organization
- Facilitate usability testing to inform design issues with product owners
- Collaborate closely with CX on user research, personas, and user journeys

OCTOBER 2009 — NOVEMBER 2016 (7 years)

## KalioCommerce — Senior User Experience Designer & Front-End Developer

- Design, build, and maintain the front-end architecture that is leveraged across all Kalio clients
- Pioneered responsive design both with clients and within the organization
- Established UX principles for the redesign of Kalio e-commerce site manager
- Create wireframes and user flows for design discussions on all e-commerce path to purchase pages
- Consult with clients to implement their e-commerce store onto the Kalio SasS platform
- · Create and maintain style guides and coding standards for both clients and internal use
- Provided leadership and training on UX and front-end development for all designers and developers both internal and external
- Lead the visual design with the client
- Analyze A/B testing to increase conversion
- Leverage analytics to inform usage patterns and increase conversion

Clients: The Republic of Tea • Arthur Beren Shoes, Inc. • AcornTV • A.M. Leonard • Positive Promotions • Taylor Corporation • Discount Ramps • Touch of Class • Hale Groves • Travers Tools • Jack Stack Barbecue • Primary Arms

JUNE 2009 — OCTOBER 2009 (5 Months)

## Construction Software Technologies — Front End Developer & Designer

AUGUST 2008 — JUNE 2009 (11 Months)

**Bridge Worldwide** — Senior Experience Planner

Clients: Kroger • Procter & Gamble

AUGUST 2004 - APRIL 2008 (3 years 9 months)

**Haverstick Consulting** — User Experience Designer

Clients: Kentucky Lottery • Greater Cincinnati Water Works • Ethicon • Basco

OCTOBER 2003 - AUGUST 2004 (11 months)

**Fusion Alliance** — Information Architect

Clients: ATA Airlines • Roche Diagnostics

MARCH 2002 - APRIL 2003 (1 year 2 months)

**Contractor** — Web Designer

Clients: FreeMarkets, Inc. • LexisNexis

MAY 1996 - FEBRUARY 2002 (5 years 10 months)

**Digineer** — User Interface Designer

Clients: Bank One • Bayer • Johnson & Johnson • Patterson Dental

### **EDUCATION**

The Ohio State University— B.S. Business Administration

### **PORTFOLIO**

http://michaelwoodruff.com

#### **RECOMMENDATIONS**

"Woody is one of the rare, true UX professionals who has been doing user-centered design long enough to learn all the ins, outs, and best practices. He's got an uncanny ability to take in huge amounts of information and map it all out into a connected system, yet also dive into a specific interaction and sweat the details over the fit and finish of the final mockups. Woody's wealth of expertise also extends to user research. Not only can he easily manage the details of recruiting and scheduling interviews, but he actually makes research participants feel heard and valued, building long-term value for the company. Woody is a strong team member, always willing to pitch in and offer constructive feedback on a design. His well-honed instincts and experience are enormously valuable assets for the whole team."

Jeff Stevenson, Product Design Team Leader at Paycor

"Woody is a seasoned professional who always delivers top quality work. I always knew that I could count on the quality of his work. He possesses problem solving skills that we would call upon to troubleshoot website issues. Woody could quickly identify the problem at the root, resolving the issue without introducing other issues or simply putting a Band-Aid on the actual root problem. His work ethic is impeccable. He was not one to require unplanned time off or to even use all of his PTO in a year. He was prepared for every meeting, and took great care with his work. He is a very competent professional."

- Kim Planet, Chief Solutions Architect, KalioCommerce

- "Woody brings a creative flair to every project he works on. His drive to understand user behaviors and to design the best interface for that user group is unparalleled. He routinely impressed me with his creativity and ability to model complex user interfaces."
- Joe Walter, Architect at dunnhumby
- "When I was just getting into Web standards, Woody was my go-to guy for answers. He still is. His extensive knowledge is applied in the sites he designs, which makes him an asset to any client who desires a site incorporating the latest in usability, accessibility, and design principles. He's also very generous in imparting his experience to colleagues. I'd consider Woody to be an asset to any team I was on."
- Lisa Ruff, Content Strategist, Instructional Designer, and E-Learning Developer at Fusion Alliance
- "Woody brought surprising depth and breadth to his position with Haverstick. He had a strong eye for graphic design, paying careful attention to interactivity and behavior as much as raw aesthetics. He also did an excellent job of keeping current and sharing the latest and greatest."
- Alex Hart, CTO at Construction Software Technologies
- "Mike "gets it" when it comes to standards based web design/development. His deep experience comes across to clients very well. He has excellent communication skills and is willing to go the extra mile. I highly recommend Mike."
- Steve Daly, Entrepreneur in Residence, Venture Lab at University of Cincinnati
- "He is a very fun person to work with and a great contributor to the team. He makes an effort to understand Customer's needs and delivers the product to their satisfaction. He is always up to date on the technical trends/aspects of User Interface design (and his Apple gadgets). It was a pleasure to work with Woody."
- **Gauri Kodkani**, Senior Software Engineer at Paycor
- "I was involved with Michael on gathering design requirements and software specifications for a client project. Michael was extremely thorough and relies heavily on his strong client skills to drive discussions to a distinct solution. He was able to create wireframes, site maps, and several design mockups in a timely manner, despite a full workload. His artistry in design achieves that rare balance of both broad appeal and intuitive user interaction. He has extensive familiarity with market trends which enables him to frame prospective client solutions, producing a mutual basis of communication."
- Clifford Adams, Product Owner at Paycor
- "Michael is a huge contributor and a strong UI designer. He is creative, technical, smart and focused. He knows how to get things done quickly and efficiently, and always goes above and beyond to ensure things are done on-time, on-budget and with the highest quality. I would recommend him highly and would welcome the opportunity to work with him again in the future."
- Christine (Hamad) Main, Software Engineering at Cintas IT

REFERENCES

Available upon request